Our grandparents' generation created an amazing system
قام أجدادنا ببناء نظامٍ مدهش
of canals and reservoirs that made it possible
من القنوات والخزانات التي أتاحت
for people to live in places where there wasn't a lot of water.
للناس العيش في أماكن لم يكن فيها الكثير من المياه.
For example, during the Great Depression,
على سبيل المثال، خلال فترة الكساد الكبير،
they created the Hoover Dam,
قاموا ببناء سد هوفر،
which in turn, created Lake Mead
والذي بدوره أنشأ بحيرة ميد
and made it possible for the cities of Las Vegas and Phoenix
مما سمح لكل من مدن لاس فيغاس وفينيكس
and Los Angeles to provide water
ولوس انجلوس بتوفير المياه
for people who lived in a really dry place.
للناس الذين يعيشون في أماكن جافة للغاية.
In the 20th century, we literally spent trillions of dollars
في القرن العشرين، أنفقنا حرفياً تريليونات الدولارات
building infrastructure to get water to our cities.
على بناء البنية التحتية لإيصال المياه إلى مدننا.
In terms of economic development, it was a great investment.
و من وجهة نظر التنمية الاقتصادية، كان ذلك استثمارا كبيرا.
But in the last decade, we've seen the combined effects
ولكن في العقد الأخير، رأينا الآثار المجتمعة
of climate change, population growth and competition for water resources
لتغيّر المناخ والنمو السكاني والتنافس على الموارد المائية
threaten these vital lifelines and water resources.
تهدد هذه السبل الحيوية والموارد المائية.
This figure shows you the change in the lake level of Lake Mead
يبين هذا المخطط التغيير في مستوى المياه في بحيرة ميد
that happened in the last 15 years.
خلال السنوات 15 الماضية.
You can see starting around the year 2000,
يمكنكم ملاحظة أنه انطلاقا من عام 2000 تقريبا،
the lake level started to drop.
بدأ مستوى البحيرة في الانخفاض.
And it was dropping at such a rate
وكان ينخفض بمعدّل
that it would have left the drinking water intakes for Las Vegas high and dry.
جعل كمية المياه الصالحة للشرب في لاس فيغاس شحيحة ونادرة.
The city became so concerned about this
أصبحت المدينة قلقة للغاية بهذا الشأن
that they recently constructed a new drinking water intake structure
لذلك شيدت مؤخرا بنية جديدة لتوفير الماء الصالح للشرب
that they referred to as the "Third Straw"
ويشار إليها باسم "الأنبوب الثالث"
to pull water out of the greater depths of the lake.
لاستخراج المياه من الأعماق الأبعد للبحيرة.
The challenges associated with providing water to a modern city
إنّ التحديات المرتبطة بتوفير المياه لمدينة حديثة
are not restricted to the American Southwest.
لا تقتصر على جنوب غرب الولايات المتحدة الأميركية.
In the year 2007, the third largest city in Australia, Brisbane,
ففي عام 2007، كانت ثالث أكبر مدينة في استراليا، بريسبان،
came within 6 months of running out of water.
أمام خطر نفاد المياه في غضون 6 أشهر.
A similar drama is playing out today in São Paulo, Brazil,
يعاد نفس السيناريو اليوم في في ساو باولو، البرازيل،
where the main reservoir for the city
حيث أنّ الخزان الرئيسي للمدينة
has gone from being completely full in 2010,
تحوّل من كونه ممتلئا تماما عام 2010،
to being nearly empty today
إلى كونه فارغا تقريبا اليوم
as the city approaches the 2016 Summer Olympics.
مع اقتراب المدينة لاحتضانها دورة الالعاب الاولمبية الصيفية لعام 2016.
For those of us who are fortunate enough
بالنسبة لأولئك الذين حالفهم الحظ منا
to live in one of the world's great cities,
للعيش في إحدى أكبر المدن في العالم،
we've never truly experienced the effects of a catastrophic drought.
لم نشهد في الحقيقة أبدا الآثار المترتبة على الجفاف الكارثي.
We like to complain about the navy showers we have to take.
فنحن نحبّ التذمر حول طريقة الاستحمام المختصر التي علينا أن نتبعها.
We like our neighbors to see our dirty cars and our brown lawns.
نحب أن يرى جيراننا سياراتنا المتسخة وعشبنا المصفر.
But we've never really faced the prospect of turning on the tap
ولكننا لم نواجه فعلا مفهوم فتح صنبورالماء
and having nothing come out.
دون أن يخرج منه شيء.
And that's because when things have gotten bad in the past,
وذلك لأن الأمور عندما كانت تسوء في الماضي،
it's always been possible to expand a reservoir
كان من الممكن دائما توسيع خزّان
or dig a few more groundwater wells.
أو حفر آبار مياه جوفية أخرى.
Well, in a time when all of the water resources are spoken for,
حسنا، في الوقت الذي كانت مصادر المياه تلقى الاهتمام،
it's not going to be possible to rely on this tried and true way
لم يعد بالإمكان الاعتماد على هذه الطريقة المجربة والواقعية
of providing ourselves with water.
في توفير المياه لأنفسنا.
Some people think that we're going to solve the urban water problem
يعتقد بعض الأشخاص أننا سنقوم بحل مشكلة المياه في المناطق الحضرية
by taking water from our rural neighbors.
بأخذ المياه من جيراننا في المناطق الريفية.
But that's an approach that's fraught with political, legal and social dangers.
ولكن هذه المقاربة محفوفة بمخاطر سياسية وقانونية واجتماعية.
And even if we succeed in grabbing the water from our rural neighbors,
وحتى لو نجحنا في الاستيلاء على الماء من جيراننا في المناطق الريفية،
we're just transferring the problem to someone else
فإننا نقوم فقط بنقل مشكلتنا إلى شخصٍ آخر
and there's a good chance it will come back and bite us
وهناك احتمال كبير في عودة المشكلة لتؤثر سلبا فينا
in the form of higher food prices
على شكل أسعار أعلى للمواد الغذائية
and damage to the aquatic ecosystems that already rely upon that water.
وأضرار بالنظم البيئية المائية التي تعتمد على ذلك الماء.
I think that there's a better way to solve our urban water crisis
أعتقد أن هنالك طريقة أفضل لحل أزمة المياه في المناطق الحضرية
and I think that's to open up four new local sources of water
وأعتقد أن ذلك بفتح أربعة مصادر محلية جديدة للمياه
that I liken to faucets.
أشبهها بالصنابير.
If we can make smart investments in these new sources of water
إن استطعنا القيام باستثمارات ذكية في هذه المصادر الجديدة للمياه
in the coming years,
في السنوات المقبلة،
we can solve our urban water problem
يمكننا حل مشكلة المياه في المناطق الحضرية
and decrease the likelihood that we'll ever run across
وتقليل احتمال تعرضنا
the effects of a catastrophic drought.
لآثار الجفاف الكارثي.
Now, if you told me 20 years ago
الآن، لو أخبرتني قبل 20 عاماً
that a modern city could exist without a supply of imported water,
أن المدينة الحديثة يمكنها أن تعيش دون إمدادات المياه المستوردة،
I probably would have dismissed you as an unrealistic and uninformed dreamer.
لقمت على الأرجح بصرفك لأنك حالم غير واقعي وغير مطّلع
But my own experiences
ولكنّ تجاربي الخاصة
working with some of the world's most water-starved cities in the last decades
خلال عملي في بعض أكثر مدن العالم شحة للمياه في العقود الماضية
have shown me that we have the technologies and the management skills
أرتني أننا نملك التقنيات ومهارات الإدارة
to actually transition away from imported water,
للانتقال بعيدا عن المياه المستوردة،
and that's what I want to tell you about tonight.
وهذا ما أريد ان أخبركم عنه هذه الليلة.
The first source of local water supply that we need to develop
المصدر الأول للمياه المحلية الذي نحتاج إلى تطويره
to solve our urban water problem
لحل مشكل المياه في المناطق الحضرية
will flow with the rainwater that falls in our cities.
هي مياه الأمطار التي تهطل في مدننا.
One of the great tragedies of urban development
من المآسي الكبيرة للتنمية الحضرية
is that as our cities grew,
هو أننا مع نمو مدننا،
we started covering all the surfaces with concrete and asphalt.
بدأنا بتغطية جميع الأسطح بالإسمنت والإسفلت.
And when we did that, we had to build storm sewers
وعندما قمنا بذلك، كان علينا بناء مجاري مياه الأمطار
to get the water that fell on the cities out
للتخلص من المياه المتساقطة في المدن
before it could cause flooding,
قبل أن تتسبب في حدوث فيضانات،
and that's a waste of a vital water resource.
وهذا إهدار لمصدر هام لمياه الشرب.
Let me give you an example.
اسمحوا لي أن أقدم لكم مثالا.
This figure here shows you the volume of water
يظهر هذا المخطط حجم المياه
that could be collected in the city of San Jose
التي يمكن جمعها في مدينة سان خوسيه
if they could harvest the stormwater that fell within the city limits.
إذا أمكنهم جمع مياه الأمطار التي تهطل ضمن حدود المدينة.
You can see from the intersection of the blue line and the black dotted line
يمكنك أن ترى من تقاطع الخط الأزرق والخط الأسود المتقطّع
that if San Jose could just capture half of the water that fell within the city,
أنه إذا تمكنت سان خوسيه من جمع نصف كمية المياه الهاطلة داخل المدينة،
they'd have enough water to get them through an entire year.
ستحصل على ما يكفيها من المياه لمدة سنة كاملة.
Now, I know what some of you are probably thinking.
أعرف ما قد يفكر فيه بعضكم.
"The answer to our problem is to start building great big tanks
"الجواب المناسب لمشكلتنا هو البدء ببناء خزانات كبيرة جدا
and attaching them to the downspouts of our roof gutters,
وربطها بفتحات أسفل الميزاب الموجود على أسطح منازلنا،
rainwater harvesting."
وذلك لجمع مياه الأمطار."
Now, that's an idea that might work in some places.
هذه فكرة يمكن أن تنجح في بعض الأماكن.
But if you live in a place where it mainly rains in the winter time
ولكن إذا كنت تعيش في مكان تهطل فيه الأمطار غالبا في فصل الشتاء
and most of the water demand is in the summertime,
ومعظم الطلب على المياه يكون في فصل الصيف،
it's not a very cost-effective way to solve a water problem.
فليست تلك وسيلة فعالة جدا من حيث التكلفة لحل مشكلة المياه.
And if you experience the effects of a multiyear drought,
وإذا واجهت آثار الجفاف لعدة سنوات،
like California's currently experiencing,
كذلك الذي تشهده كاليفورنيا حاليا،
you just can't build a rainwater tank that's big enough to solve your problem.
لا يمكن بناء خزان مياه أمطار كبيرا بما يكفي لحل المشكلة.
I think there's a lot more practical way
أعتقد أنه توجد طريقة أكثر عملية
to harvest the stormwater and the rainwater that falls in our cities,
لجمع مياه الأمطار الهاطلة في مدننا،
and that's to capture it and let it percolate into the ground.
وذلك بجمعها وتركها تتسرب إلى باطن الأرض.
After all, many of our cities are sitting on top of a natural water storage system
في النهاية، تقع الكثير من مدننا فوق أنظمة تخزين مياه طبيعية
that can accommodate huge volumes of water.
يمكنها استيعاب كميات ضخمة من المياه.
For example, historically, Los Angeles has obtained
على سبيل المثال، ومن الناحية التاريخية، حصلت لوس انجلوس
about a third of its water supply from a massive aquifer
على حوالي ثلث إمدادات مياهها من طبقة مياه جوفية ضخمة
that underlies the San Fernando Valley.
تقع تحت وادي سان فرناندو.
Now, when you look at the water that comes off of your roof
الآن, عندما تنظر إلى الماء المتساقط من فوق سطح المنزل
and runs off of your lawn and flows down the gutter,
ثم يجري فوق العشب ويتدفق إلى أسفل البالوعة,
you might say to yourself, "Do I really want to drink that stuff?"
قد تقول لنفسك, "هل أرغب حقاً بشرب هذا؟"
Well, the answer is you don't want to drink it
حسنا, الجواب هو أنك لا تريد أن تشربه
until it's been treated a little bit.
حتى تتمّ معالجته قليلا.
And so the challenge that we face in urban water harvesting
وهكذا فإن التحدي الذي نواجهه في جمع المياه في المناطق الحضرية
is to capture the water, clean the water
هو حبس المياه, وتنقيتها
and get it underground.
وإرسالها إلى باطن الأرض.
And that's exactly what the city of Los Angeles is doing
وهذا بالضبط ما تقوم به مدينة لوس أنجلس
with a new project that they're building in Burbank, California.
مع المشروع الجديد الذين يقومون بإنجازه في بربانك، كاليفورنيا.
This figure here shows the stormwater park that they're building
يُظهرهذا الرسم مجمع مياه الأمطار الذين يعملون على بناءه
by hooking a series of stormwater collection systems, or storm sewers,
من خلال ربط سلسلة من أنظمة جمع مياه الأمطار, أو المجاري
and routing that water into an abandoned gravel quarry.
وتوجيهها نحو مقلع حصى مهجور.
The water that's captured in the quarry
إنّ المياه التي تم جمعها في المقلع
is slowly passed through a man-made wetland,
تمر ببطء عبر أراض رطبة اصطناعية
and then it goes into that ball field there
وثم تدخل في ملعب الكرة ذلك
and percolates into the ground,
وتتسرب إلى باطن الأرض,
recharging the drinking water aquifer of the city.
لتغذية المياه الجوفية الصالحة للشرب في المدينة.
And in the process of passing through the wetland
وخلال عملية مرور المياه عبر الاراضي الرطبة
and percolating through the ground,
ونفوذها إلى باطن الأرض,
the water encounters microbes that live on the surfaces of the plants
تتعرض المياه للميكروبات الموجودة على اسطح النباتات
and the surfaces of the soil,
وسطح التربة,
and that purifies the water.
وهذا يقوم بتنقية المياه.
And if the water's still not clean enough to drink
وإن بقيت المياه غير نقيّة بما فيه الكفاية لتُشرب
after it's been through this natural treatment process,
بعد خضوعها لعملية المعالجة الطبيعية,
the city can treat it again
يمكن للمدينة معالجتها ثانية
when they pump if back out of the groundwater aquifers
عندما يتم ضخها من طبقات المياه الجوفية الى الخارج
before they deliver it to people to drink.
قبل أن يتم ايصالها إلى الناس لشربها.
The second tap that we need to open up to solve our urban water problem
الصنبور الثاني الذي نحتاج فتحه لحل مشكلة المياه في المناطق الحضرية
will flow with the wastewater
سيجري مع مياه الصرف الصحي
that comes out of our sewage treatment plants.
التي تخرج من محطات معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي.
Now, many of you are probably familiar with the concept of recycled water.
الكثير منكم مطلّع على الأرجح على مفهوم المياه المعاد تدويرها.
You've probably seen signs like this
ربما رأيتم علامات مثل هذه
that tell you that the shrubbery and the highway median
تخبر أن الشجيرات والجزرات الوسطية في الطرق السريعة
and the local golf course
وملعب الغولف المحلي
is being watered with water
يتم سقيها بماء
that used to be in a sewage treatment plant.
مصدره محطة معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي.
We've been doing this for a couple of decades now.
اننا نقوم بذلك منذ بضع عقود.
But what we're learning from our experience
ولكن ما تعلمناه من تجربتنا
is that this approach is much more expensive that we expected it to be.
هو أن هذا الأسلوب أكثر تكلفة مما كنا نتوقع.
Because once we build the first few water recycling systems
فبعد بناءنا أنظمة إعادة تدوير المياه القليلة الأولى
close to the sewage treatment plant,
قريبة من محطة معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي,
we have to build longer and longer pipe networks
يتوجب علينا بناء شبكات أنابيب أطول فأطول
to get that water to where it needs to go.
لايصال ذلك الماء إلى الوجهة المختارة.
And that becomes prohibitive in terms of cost.
ويصبح ذلك باهض الكلفة.
What we're finding is
ما اكتشفناه هو
that a much more cost-effective and practical way of recycling wastewater
أن أكثر وسيلة فعالة من حيث التكلفة وأكثرعملية لإعادة تدوير مياه الفضلات
is to turn treated wastewater into drinking water
هو تحويل مياه الصرف الصحي المعالجة إلى مياه للشرب
through a two-step process.
باعتماد عملية من خطوتين.
In the first step in this process we pressurize the water
في الخطوة الأولى من هذه العملية نقوم بضغط المياه
and pass it through a reverse osmosis membrane:
ونجعلها تمر عبر غشاء تناضح عكسي:
a thin, permeable plastic membrane
غشاء نفّاذ بلاستيكي رقيق
that allows water molecules to pass through
يسمح بمرور جزيئات الماء من خلاله
but traps and retains the salts, the viruses and the organic chemicals
ولكن يحتجز الأملاح, والفيروسات و الكيمياويات العضوية
that might be present in the wastewater.
التي قد توجد في مياه الصرف الصحي.
In the second step in the process,
في الخطوة الثانية من هذه العملية,
we add a small amount of hydrogen peroxide
نضيف كمية صغيرة من بيروكسيد الهيدروجين
and shine ultraviolet light on the water.
ونسلّط أشعة فوق بنفسجية على الماء.
The ultraviolet light cleaves the hydrogen peroxide
تخترق الأشعة فوق البنفسجية بيروكسيد الهيدروجين
into two parts that are called hydroxyl radicals,
وتقسمه قسمين يطلق عليها جذور الهيدروكسيل,
and these hydroxyl radicals are very potent forms of oxygen
وهي أشكال قوية جدا من الأكسجين
that break down most organic chemicals.
تقوم بتفكيك معظم المواد الكيميائية العضوية.
After the water's been through this two-stage process,
بعد خضوع المياه إلى العملية ذات المرحلتين هذه,
it's safe to drink.
تصبح صالحة للشرب.
I know,
أعرف,
I've been studying recycled water
درست المياه المعاد تدويرها
using every measurement technique known to modern science
باستعمال كل أساليب القياس المعروفة في العلم الحديث
for the past 15 years.
على مدى السنوات 15 الماضية.
We've detected some chemicals
اكتشفنا بعض المواد الكيميائية
that can make it through the first step in the process,
التي يمكنها تخطّي المرحلة الأولى من العملية,
but by the time we get to the second step,
ولكن مع بلوغنا المرحلة الثانية,
the advanced oxidation process,
عملية الأكسدة المتقدمة,
we rarely see any chemicals present.
نادرا ما نسجّل وجود أي مواد كيميائية.
And that's in stark contrast to the taken-for-granted water supplies
على النقيض من مصادر المياه المُسلم بها
that we regularly drink all the time.
التي نشربها طوال الوقت بشكلٍ منتظم.
There's another way we can recycle water.
هنالك طريقة أخرى تسمح بإعادة تدوير المياه.
This is an engineered treatment wetland that we recently built
هذه أراضي معالجة رطبة صناعية بنيناها مؤخرا
on the Santa Ana River in Southern California.
على نهر سانتا آنا جنوب كاليفورنيا.
The treatment wetland receives water from a part of the Santa Ana River
وتتلقى اراضي المعالجة الرطبة الماء من جزء من نهر سانتا آنا
that in the summertime consists almost entirely of wastewater effluent
يتشكل في فصل الصيف بصورة كليّة تقريبا من تدفق مياه الصرف الصحي
from cities like Riverside and San Bernardino.
القادمة من مدن مثل ريفرسايد وسان برناردينو.
The water comes into our treatment wetland,
ويتجه الماء إلى أراضي المعالجة الرطبة,
it's exposed to sunlight and algae
فيتعرض إلى أشعة الشمس والطحالب
and those break down the organic chemicals,
حيث يقوم اولئك بتفتيت المواد الكيميائية العضوية,
remove the nutrients and inactivate the waterborne pathogens.
وإزالة المواد الغذائية وتثبيط العوامل الممرضة التي تنقلها المياه.
The water gets put back in the Santa Ana River,
تُعاد المياه مرة أخرى إلى نهر سانتا آنا,
it flows down to Anaheim,
وتجري باتجاه أنهايم,
gets taken out at Anaheim and percolated into the ground,
تؤخذ في أنهايم, ويتم انفاذها الى الأرض.
and becomes the drinking water of the city of Anaheim,
وتُصبح مياه الشرب لمدينة أنهايم,
completing the trip from the sewers of Riverside County
مكملة الرحلة من مجاري مقاطعة ريفرسايد
to the drinking water supply of Orange County.
لإمدادات مياه الشرب في مقاطعة أورانج.
Now, you might think that this idea of drinking wastewater
قد تعتقد أن هذه الفكرة عن شرب مياه الصرف الصحي
is some sort of futuristic fantasy or not commonly done.
هي نوع من الخيال المستقبلي أو ليس من المعتاد تنفيذها.
Well, in California, we already recycle about 40 billion gallons a year
حسنا، في كاليفورنيا، نقوم بالفعل بتدوير حوالي 40 مليار جالون في السنة
of wastewater through the two-stage advanced treatment process
من مياه الصرف الصحي باعتماد عملية المعالجة المتقدمة ذات المرحلتين
I was telling you about.
التي كنت أخبركم عنها.
That's enough water to be the supply of about a million people
وتلك كمية كافية من المياه لتزوّد حوالي مليون شخص
if it were their sole water supply.
ان كانت مصدرهم الوحيد للمياه.
The third tap that we need to open up will not be a tap at all,
الصنبور الثالث الذي نحتاج إلى فتحه لن يكون صنبوراً،
it will be a kind of virtual tap,
سيكون نوعا عملياً من الصنابير,
it will be the water conservation that we manage to do.
سيكون ذلك الحفاظ على المياه التي نستعملها.
And the place where we need to think about water conservation is outdoors
والمكان الذي نحتاج فيه إلى التفكير بالمحافظة على المياه هو خارج المنزل
because in California and other modern American cities,
لأنه في ولاية كاليفورنيا وغيرها من المدن الأمريكية الحديثة,
about half of our water use happens outdoors.
حوالي نصف ما نستخدمه من المياه يكون خارج المنزل.
In the current drought,
في الجفاف الحالي,
we've seen that it's possible
رأينا أنه يمكن
to have our lawns survive and our plants survive
للعشب والنباتات البقاء على قيد الحياة
with about half as much water.
بحوالي نصف كمية الماء.
So there's no need to start painting concrete green
لذلك لا توجد حاجة لبدء صبغ الخرسانة بالأخضر
and putting in Astroturf and buying cactuses.
واعتماد العشب الصناعي وشراء نبات الصبار.
We can have California-friendly landscaping with soil moisture detectors
يمكننا إنشاء حدائق صديقة لكاليفورنيا مع كاشفات لرطوبة التربة
and smart irrigation controllers
وحدات ذكية للتحكم بالري
and have beautiful green landscapes in our cities.
والحصول على حدائق خضراء جميلة في مدننا.
The fourth and final water tap that we need to open up
الصنبور الرابع والأخير الذي نحتاج فتحه
to solve our urban water problem
لحل مشكل المياه في المناطق الحضرية
will flow with desalinated seawater.
سيكون مياه البحر المحلاة.
Now, I know what you probably heard people say about seawater desalination.
أعلم ما قد سمعتم عما يقوله الناس عن تحلية مياه البحر.
"It's a great thing to do if you have lots of oil, not a lot of water
"إنه لأمر عظيم أن تقوم بذلك إذا كنت تملك الكثير من النفط, وليس الكثير من الماء
and you don't care about climate change."
ولم تكن تبالي بالتغير المناخي".
Seawater desalination is energy-intensive no matter how you slice it.
تعتبر تحلية مياه البحر مستهلكة للطاقة مهما قمت بتجزئتها.
But that characterization of seawater desalination
ولكن هذا التوصيف لتحلية مياه البحر
as being a nonstarter is hopelessly out of date.
بأنها غير مجدية قد عفا عليه الزمن.
We've made tremendous progress in seawater desalination
لقد حققنا تقدما هائلا في تحلية مياه البحر
in the past two decades.
في العقدين الماضيين.
This picture shows you
تظهر لكم هذه الصورة
the largest seawater desalination plant in the Western hemisphere
أكبر محطة لتحلية مياه البحر في النصف الغربي من الكرة الأرضية
that's currently being built north of San Diego.
التي لازالت في طور البناء شمال سان دييغو.
Compared to the seawater desalination plant
بالمقارنة بمحطة تحلية مياه البحر
that was built in Santa Barbara 25 years ago,
التي بُنيت في سانتا باربرا قبل 25 عاما,
this treatment plant will use about half the energy
ستستخدم هذه المحطة حوالي نصف الطاقة
to produce a gallon of water.
لإنتاج غالون واحد من الماء.
But just because seawater desalination has become less energy-intensive,
ولكن كون تحلية مياه البحر أصبحت أقل استهلاكا للطاقة,
doesn't mean we should start building desalination plants everywhere.
لا يعني أنه يجب علينا بناء محطات تحلية المياه في كل مكان.
Among the different choices we have,
من بين الخيارات المختلفة المتاحة,
it's probably the most energy-intensive
فهي على الأرجح الأكثراستهلاكا للطاقة
and potentially environmentally damaging
والاكثر ضررا بالبيئة
of the options to create a local water supply.
بين الخيارات المتوفرة لإمدادات المياه المحلية.
So there it is.
لذا فالأمر هكذا.
With these four sources of water,
مع هذه المصادر الأربعة للماء,
we can move away from our reliance on imported water.
يمكننا الابتعاد عن اعتمادنا على المياه المستوردة.
Through reform in the way we landscape our surfaces and our properties,
من خلال ادخال إصلاحات في طريقة انشائنا مسطحاتنا وملكيّاتنا،
we can reduce outdoor water use by about 50 percent,
يمكننا التقليل من استخدام المياه خارج المنزل بنحو 50 بالمئة,
thereby increasing the water supply by 25 percent.
ومن ثمّ زيادة إمدادات المياه بنسبة 25 في المئة.
We can recycle the water that makes it into the sewer,
يمكننا إعادة تدوير مياه المجاري,
thereby increasing our water supply by 40 percent.
وبالتالي زيادة إمدادات المياه بنسبة 40 في المئة.
And we can make up the difference through a combination
ويمكننا تعويض هذا الفارق من خلال مزج
of stormwater harvesting and seawater desalination.
جمع مياه الأمطار وتحلية مياه البحر.
So, let's create a water supply
لذا، لنقم بإنشاء إمدادات مياه
that will be able to withstand any of the challenges
من شأنها الصمود أمام أي من التحديات
that climate change throws at us in the coming years.
التي يخلقها تغيرالمناخ في السنوات المقبلة.
Let's create a water supply that uses local sources
دعونا ننشئ إمدادات مياه تستخدم مصادر محلية
and leaves more water in the environment for fish and for food.
وتترك المزيد من المياه في البيئة للأسماك والأغذية.
Let's create a water system that's consistent with out environmental values.
دعونا ننشئ نظام مياه يتفق مع قيمنا البيئية.
And let's do it for our children and our grandchildren
ولنفعل ذلك لأجل أطفالنا وأحفادنا
and let's tell them this is the system
ولنخبرهم أن هذا هو النظام
that they have to take care of in the future
الذي عليهم الاعتناء به في المستقبل
because it's our last chance to create a new kind of water system.
لأنها فرصتنا الأخيرة لانشاء نوع جديد من أنظمة المياه.
Thank you very much for your attention.
شكرا جزيلا لانتباهكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)